<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    
    <title>Lagrangians to Lasers</title>
    
    
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      <item>
        <title>Can ML Accelerate Particle Simulations?</title>
        <description>
          Experimental High Energy Physics - 
          Over the last decade, machine learning techniques have been widely adopted by various domains in particle physics. I will discuss using such ML algorithms and simulations in particle physics analysis and the challenges they present. Then, I will introduce a...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2024-04-11-chitrakshee-yede/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2024-04-11-chitrakshee-yede/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Studying Invisible Giants: Measuring SMBH masses using Schwarzschild modelling</title>
        <description>
          Astrophysics - 
          Supermassive Black Holes are (like the name implies) extremely massive black holes, weighing up to billions of times the mass of the Sun, present in the centers of galaxies. By their nature, they are also invisible and thus very difficult...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2024-04-04-anirban_roy_chowdhury/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2024-04-04-anirban_roy_chowdhury/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tachyons: Time Travelers or Theoretical Quandaries?</title>
        <description>
          Theoretical Particle Physics - 
          Discuss what tachyons are, how they might make sense, how we tried (and failed) to detect them, and how they still don’t actually make sense for the most part but are an interesting topic of discussion nonetheless.

        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2024-03-21-abhilash-sengupta/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2024-03-21-abhilash-sengupta/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Langmuir Probe Analysis of Plasma</title>
        <description>
          Plasma Physics - 
          The Langmuir probe is the most fundamental diagnostics technique for extracting plasma parameters such as electron temperature, plasma density, and plasma potential. I will explain how I analyzed the Langmuir probe data of RF-produced plasma. I will also discuss an...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2024-03-14-shalini-das/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2024-03-14-shalini-das/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Growing Thin Films</title>
        <description>
          Nanotechnology - 
          I will give a motivation for why thin films are interesting and worth studying and growing. I will then talk about the various ways in which we can grow thin films and the merits and demerits of each technique. I...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2024-03-07-dhairya-bhandari/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2024-03-07-dhairya-bhandari/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What it takes to build an Ultra-Stable Laser?</title>
        <description>
          Optics - 
          Throughout history, precise measurement has been crucial in gaining a deeper understanding of the nature of things and even rewriting the laws of physics. The science of measuring with extreme precision is fascinating in itself, but what’s equally intriguing is...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2024-02-29-gautham-upadhyaya/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2024-02-29-gautham-upadhyaya/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introduction to Random Matrix Theory</title>
        <description>
          Statistical Physics - 
          In Physics, one of the major goals is to construct good theoretical models that explain the observations in the physical world. Can the spectra of matrices with random entries serve as useful models for some physical systems? Turns out the...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Feb 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2024-02-15-soham-chandak/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2024-02-15-soham-chandak/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Search for new physics at the Large Hadron Collider</title>
        <description>
          Experimental High Energy Physics - 
          Despite the success of the Standard Model in describing the interactions of elementary particles, observations that suggest the existence of additional phenomena remain. Many theories of physics beyond the Standard Model have been proposed that feature “final states” in high-energy...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 08 Feb 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2024-02-08-shreyas-bakare/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2024-02-08-shreyas-bakare/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reconstruction of Euler-Heisenberg Lagrangians</title>
        <description>
          Condensed Matter Physics - 
          The Euler-Heisenberg Lagrangian (EHL) refers to non-linear corrections to Maxwell’s equations due to the interaction of electromagnetic fields with vacuum fluctuations of a charged field. One of the most exciting predictions of this formalism is the spontaneous production of particle...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Aug 2023 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2023-08-28-drishti-gupta/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2023-08-28-drishti-gupta/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Delaminating CVD Graphene</title>
        <description>
          Condensed Matter Physics - 
          Graphene is the poster child of 2D materials, and has diverse properties that suit it for a wide range of applications. Here, I will discuss how we can transfer graphene from one substrate to another, in order to harness these...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2023 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2023-08-21-dhairya-bhandari/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2023-08-21-dhairya-bhandari/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
